<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peters enlargement vpon the prayers of the Church. By Master Harris</title>
            <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12839.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120172</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855371</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 599:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Peters enlargement vpon the prayers of the Church. By Master Harris</title>
                  <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Iohn Bartlett, and are to be sould at the golden Cup, in the Gold-smiths Rowe in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Acts XII, 6-7.</note>
                  <note>Differs from the first edition in that it has an added preface.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 12340b on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20861:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20861:1"/>
            <p>PETERS ENLARGEMENT VPON THE PRAYERS OF THE CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> Maſter HARRIS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 34.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Righteous cry and the Lord heareth and deliuereth them out of all their troubles.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlett,</hi> and are to be ſould at the golden Cup in the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Rowe in Cheapſide. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20861:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20861:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon (thus made vp with mine owne and others notes) I now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Authority and Cenſure, for ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I yeelde heere is no more then what was deliuered, whether no leſſe I haue not now to ſay, for cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance (I yeeld to the allegation) I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it ſeaſonable. The times ſhall euer bee cleared by prayer whenſoeuer they looke ſadly vpon vs. Our Brethren abroad cry ſtil in the Churches words. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>The harveſt is paſt, and the Summer is ended, and we are not holpen,</hi> and wee (methinks) ſhould add with <hi>Ieremie</hi> verſe 21. <hi>I am ſore vexed for the hurt of the daughter of my people, I am heauie, aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath taken me; Is there no balme at Gilead &amp;c,</hi> At home, howſoeuer the Lord hath beene gracious to vs in the ſcarcitie, yet we may
<pb facs="tcp:20861:3"/>in moſt places, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.20.</note> take vp the Prophets words in another ſence, <hi>Is the ſeede yet in the Barne? as yet the Trees haue not beene deliuered of their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then?</hi> Looke into the 65 <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 65.9. <hi>10.11.</hi>
               </note> and thou ſhalt find that it is the Lord that finds both ground and ſeede, that giues both growth and ripening to the Corne, and therefore wee ſhould waite vpon him with our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents of praiſe &amp; prayer, this were enough to make vs pray, but this is the leaſt of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny motiues, for <hi>Reader</hi> thou ſeeſt the times, the World is now all eare and tongue, the moſt giuen with the <hi>Athenians</hi> to little els then to heare and tell newes, (vncertaine newes, <note place="margin">Demonol. l. 3 c. 1. ad finem.</note> the Authour of all lies as his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hath told vs) the reſt are willing alſo to heare, and to heare Gods Truth, not Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and therein they doe but as S. <hi>Iames</hi> would haue them, ſo as they would add doing to hearing as hee commaunds. But alas, whilſt we only profeſſe and diſcourſe of Religion, we driue the practiſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion out of the world, as one too iuſtly complaines. <note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. Ral.</hi> preface</note> It is lamentable to conſider the little vſe that is made of Gods Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in moſt places; Preachers too often (I
<pb facs="tcp:20861:3"/>tremble to ſpeake it) be vſed like poſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſpurd on till they be ſpent, and then a freſh is called for, in the meane the world ſits ſtill and thinks to be ſaued for hearing. <hi>Reader,</hi> Mourne for this, weepe for this, for this boades a Iudgement, the Lord will rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon for the blood of his Prophets ſpent as well as ſhed. To theſe reaſons, it will not be hard for thee to add more, looke within thee, and round about thee, and ſo ſtirre vp thy ſelfe to this exerciſe of Prayer, an exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe (I can aſſure thee) of vnſpeakable ſtrength and comfort, an exerciſe without which thou canſt not liue, and by which thou mayeſt liue in the mouth of death. Beleeue it, wert thou in an eſtate, more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate then death, in a place worſe then hell, yet if there thou couldeſt pray truely, thou ſhouldſt find comfort and ſtrength beyond hope, for Prayer is better then our hopes, and yet God is better to vs then our prayer. Firſt, for that which is publique, follow him who was no time-ſerver, make no ſmall account of publique prayers. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for priuat, pauſe before thou ſpeak, remember who ſpake it, if a man would
<pb facs="tcp:20861:4"/>not deliuer an Oration to a Prince <hi>extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> and ſo dainely, it will not become vs to open our mouths raſhly before our maker, ſecondly, keepe touch with God: firſt, for extraordinary and incidental occaſions, be ſure to keepe thy ſelfe in ſuch a ſtate and condition of ſoule, as that euer thou canſt recollect thy ſelfe, and call in all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſoule for this buſineſſe vpon a ſhort warning: ſecondly, for ordinary times, ſo neare as may bee, faile not of thine houre, when the Clocke ſtrikes the Schollar runs to his booke, thou muſt to God leauing al, there tender thy ſelfe, though not alwaies alike fit, and ſo be in the way and place of preferment, if words will not come, ſigh, <hi>God heares the ſighing of his priſoners,</hi> if thou canſt not ſigh, breath, God hath an eare for that, <hi>Lam</hi> 3.56. However, there be, there ſtand, and the child that ſtands before his father and appeares in his place at ſupper time with his trencher in his hand, ſpeakes with his countenance, and ſpeeds accordingly: he was wiſe who ſaid, <note place="margin">M. <hi>Gr.</hi>
               </note> they pray not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of faſhion, who ſee their infirmitie in praying and are grieued for it, the worſt
<pb facs="tcp:20861:4"/>prayers that wee make(to our owne ſence I meane) ſpeede euer beſt, and then wee pray moſt happily, when wee ariſe moſt humbled.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when thou haſt prayed, do not as children, who neuer looke after their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; but as <hi>Daniell cap.</hi> 9.1. take notice of thine enlargements in prayer and of thy ſucceſſe after, write downe time and place as the Prophet doth, and ſo helpe thy ſelfe in future times by former experiments, I ſee this Porch growes wide, and therefore I wil conclude, if thou be acquainted with prayer, thou knoweſt there is more in it then can be expreſſed, if thou bee not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, grow acquainted, and thou ſhalt find me true, if thou wanteſt furtheſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and directions, I commend (in this haſt) to thee who art but a poore Engliſh priuate man. Firſt, for the promiſes (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the heart muſt chew before prayer) the <hi>Treatiſe of faith.</hi> ſecondly, for motiues, the <hi>Epiſtle to the key Heauen.</hi> thirdly, for caſes of Conſcience and directions after prayer, 2. <hi>Treatiſes</hi> on <hi>Ephe</hi> 6. <hi>viz. the ſpiritual Armour,</hi> and now after directions and exhortations, what remaines but practiſe, in ſtead of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:20861:5"/>prailing and enter dealing in State-bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſines, do thou pray, pray for thy Soveraign, for his ſeede, for the Churches, for thy ſelf, for thy charge, and vſe no more words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mens ſinnes, then thou wilt make prayers for their ſoules in ſecret, if thou wilt haue comfort in thy wordes: Thus much of this, Now <hi>Reader</hi> to thee, if theſe plaine notes paſſe the Preſſe, know that I neither did ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their publiſhing before I preached them, nor can intend notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their refining ſince; if the world may be bettered by them, or by any thing I can doe, I haue enough, onely I deſire mercy and equitie from my friends, thoſe notes of mine which they haue, I will my ſelfe (after my publique Miniſterie) now ſhortly reviſe, let no man doe ſo ill an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as to thruſt out other mens notes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their privitie, eſpecially his, who can doe nothing worthy this Age.</p>
            <p>RO: HARRIS.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20861:5"/>
            <head>PETERS ENLARGEMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 12.6.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And when Herod would haue brought him forth, the ſame night Peter was ſleeping between two ſouldiers, bound with two chaines; and the Keepers before the doore, kept the priſon.</p>
                  <p>And behold the Angell of the Lord came vpon him, and a light ſhined in the priſon: and hee ſmote Peter on the ſide, and raiſed him vp, ſaying; Ariſe vp quickly, And his chaines fell off from his hands, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ERE is a ſtorie of <hi>Peters,</hi> 1. Impriſonment. 2. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement: With the cauſe of the one, and meanes of the other. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> hauing vexed ſome, ſlaine a ſecond, now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the third; and all this to gratifie the Iewes. <hi>Peter</hi> thus committed, is bailed by the Church, or rather remooved and freed by petition; they pray heartily for him, in the 5. verſe, and they ſpeed as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20861:6"/>happily, whileſt they are praying, God giues in the priſoner amongſt them. The manner of his delivery is here reported, and that was very ſtrange, beyond <hi>Herods</hi> purpoſe, the priſoners expectation, the Keepers meaning, all mens hopes: <hi>Herod</hi> held his purpoſe he had begun, and the next morning he meant an end of him, <hi>Peter</hi> had made his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to morrow (thinkes he) (for meſſages paſt betweene him and the Church, which ſpent this night in Prayer for him, and therefore knew the danger) I muſt be put to it, therefore I will ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my ſelfe to night: The Keepers ſtood vpon their guard, and reſolved that no <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould paſſe them: yet is <hi>Peter</hi> delivered, and how I pray you? God remoues all impediments, for nothing was in readineſſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for man, entrance was there none, therefore God ſends an Angell, and there was no ſtop againſt him.</p>
            <p>Next, in the darke, it was hard to find which was which; God directs an Angell to him, and hee comes vpon him, and miſſes not the man, though bound to the ſame chaine with two others, as in ſtrict impriſonments they vſed to doe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they were in the darke, and that was ill for noyſe; The Angell brings his darke lanthorne with him, and <hi>ſhines</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> and none elſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the priſoner can doe little for himſelfe, he is <hi>aſleepe,</hi> the Angell <hi>wakes</hi> him; he is <hi>laid,</hi> the Angell <hi>raiſes</hi> him; he is <hi>amazed,</hi> the Angell <hi>directs</hi> him; he is <hi>bound,</hi> the Angell <hi>vnties</hi> him; hee knowes not <hi>where he is,</hi> the Angell <hi>guides</hi> him; hee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20861:6"/>is to paſſe through ſundry <hi>difficulties,</hi> the Angell <hi>conducts</hi> him through them all, and ſo diſmiſſes him.</p>
            <p>Wee will vſe no more words about a plaine Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but acquaint you with our meditations: they containe the ſucceſſe of the Churches prayers; <hi>they prayed for Peter,</hi> the Angell thereupon is ſent to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> where ſee; 1. <hi>How the Angell findes him:</hi> 2. <hi>How the Angell delivers him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, he findes him <hi>ſleeping,</hi> in the midſt of feares and foes: From whence was this ſleepe, was it worldly ſorrow that cauſed it, or was it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſecuritie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In doubtfull things charitie ſuppoſes the beſt; ſo ſhould we, worldly ſorrow cauſes ſleepe, but how? when it is not extreame, and that ſleepe is ioyned with ſtarting: carnall ſecuritie will cauſe ſleepe, but why ſhould we charge <hi>Peter</hi> with that at this time; his ſleepe came from a better cauſe, he was at peace with God, he had the Churches pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for him, the cauſe for him, his conſcience for him, God and his Angels for him; he could die but once, and for one death hee was prepared: hence his boldnes before, Chapters 4. and 5. hence his confidence, here he reſolued with <hi>Dauid, I will lay me downe and ſleepe,</hi> and withall, God gaue reſt to his beloued, as it is in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> reſt more then ordinary to his minde, to his body: hence the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell can hardly awake him, and being awaked, he is not terrified, as a guiltie perſon would haue beene in this caſe: doe then but conſider, 1. The man. 2. His behaviour in like caſes. 3. The time and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20861:7"/>circumſtances. 4. The exerciſes of the Church for him. 5. The meſſenger, and meſſage ſent to him. 6. The manner of his behaviour when he is awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and you will ſee that his ſleepe grew not from diſtemper, but from ſtrength of faith and comfort.</p>
            <p>Now to the Points.</p>
            <p>Where firſt from the order, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> ſee the power of ioynt prayers, they beare downe all before them, and prevaile in heaven and earth, as the Word that comes from heaven, proſpers in the thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto it is ſent; <note place="margin">Eſay 55.</note> ſo the word that goes to heaven, the prayers of the Church ſirike vp to God, there they lie at his gates, and never will away without their errand, and when they are anſwered, then they come downe with authoritie, and raigne over all impediments below, witneſſe this Story: <hi>Peter</hi> is committed, the perſecuters are reſolute, the foes many, the friends few, meanes none but God, to God the Church goes; the enemies plotte, the Church prayes; they ſhut the priſon doores, the Church opens heavens doores; ſo ther's old tug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for the priſoner, but the Church winnes him. God, to let them ſee what prayers bee, ſends him to them while they are praying; there, ſaith God (if you will rake no deniall) there he is; thereby pointing vs to the meanes of his deliverance: we need not many words for proofe of this, <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>The prayer of one righteous man prevailes much;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iames 5.</note> if of one, what of twentie! what of an hundred! and he inſtances in <hi>Elijah, Hee alone could open and ſhut heaven,</hi> then well may many open and ſhut priſons on earth: nay adde further, the ioynt prayers of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20861:7"/>vnbeleevers and hypocrites haue done much: when heatheniſh <hi>Niniuie</hi> faſted and prayed, God heard; <note place="margin">Jonah 3.</note> when falſe <hi>Rehoboam</hi> humbled himſelfe and his people, <note place="margin">2 Chron. 12.</note> God was intreated; how much more ſhall the faithfull prayers of the Church prevaile, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile (I ſay) both for the preventing and removing evils, and obtaining and keeping of good things: What ſhall we inſtance the life of <hi>Aſa, Iehoſaphat, Hezekiah,</hi> when was it otherwiſe, when did the Church of God euer ioyne in a common petition to God but they ſped? no inſtance to the contrary.</p>
            <p>No marvell, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> this exerciſe is well grounded and warranted, it hath the warrant of a Precept: <note place="margin">Iames 5.</note>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Pray for one another; call vpon me.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The warrant of a promiſe, <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> 
                     <hi>I will deliuer thee.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The warrant of experience, never any yet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it but they prevailed.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Prayers are preſents very welcome to God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> he prefers them to all ſacrifices, being immediate wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of his Maieſtie; Let me heare thy voyce it is pleaſant: No father loues the voyce of his children, like as God loues the voyce of his Church; <note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Tis his muſicke and perfume.</hi> Rev. 5.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The parties are very deare who tender them, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> God loues his Church aboue all creatures, he gaue his Sonne for her, and therefore her ſutes ſhall haue acceptance: <hi>Let me ſee thy face, its comely;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Eſther</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pleaſed <hi>Ahaſueroſh</hi> ſo well, as the Church plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The parties from and through whom they are preſented, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> pleaſe: They are indited and abbet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the holy Ghoſt, <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. tendred by Chriſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20861:8"/>Ieſus, and ſhall theſe be denyed? adde to this:</p>
            <p n="5">5. The party to whom they are directed, to God, who is all truth, mercy, grace, wiſedome, power, and ſhall not theſe prevaile? Prayers ſet God on worke, and all in God, his wiſedome, his power, his Angels, and what then can hinder?</p>
            <p>Looke backward, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> and call to minde your ſinne this day, ſee, many a <hi>Peter</hi> hath beene in priſon, and prayers were not made by the Church; many a member ſicke, and prayers were not made by the Elders; yea many a Church diſtreſſed, <hi>Bohemia</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and <hi>Valtoline</hi> diſtreſſed, yet we did not pray; the enemy could curſe, but wee did not pray, and therefore how iuſtly might God diſtreſſe and leaue vs deſtitute of his helpe, and the Churches prayers?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Looke forward, and preſerue and improue this your intereſt in God, let no <hi>Peter,</hi> no Preacher, no Chriſtian, no neighbour lie in the chaines by you (whether in the chaines of ſickneſſe, or pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or debt, or paine, or ſinne, or temptation) but doe you repriue him: you haue a key that will open any locke, a medicine that will heale any wound, a weapon that will prevaile in any place; draw this weapon, vſe this medicine: if men be ſicke, pray them whole, if poore, pray them rich; if ſad, pray them merry.</p>
            <p>But is this ſo eaſily done? yes verily by the whole Church; as it is for the outward eſtate when one is very poore, it is hard for two or three to ſet him vp againe, but nothing for a thouſand; and when one is in a pit, it is much for one, but not for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20861:8"/>many to pull him out: ſee here, it is long of vs that men lie ſo long vnder their burdens, would wee ioyntly commend them to God, our prayers would take, mens chaines would off, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> true ſpirituall chaines: Why if ſo, were it not worth the while? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> what, may wee eaſe our brethren of temptations, of paſſions, of luſts, and will wee not? But for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward croſſes, ſaith not Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> let the prayers of the Church heale the ſicke; ſaith not the ſtory, the prayers of the Church procured <hi>Peters</hi> liberty? But ſay they bee not alwayes delivered? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> yet it is good to get the croſſes mitigated, ſanctified, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſomething will be done if wee pray; doe this then or nothing: perhaps you will excuſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther negligences, you would viſit your ſicke neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but you queſtion, his diſeaſe, your welcome; you would relieue your poore neighbours, but you haue it not; why there is no Chriſtian man but hee hath an intereſt in God, a ſpirit of prayer; lift vp a prayer for thy brethren, if thou canſt doe nothing elſe, and this will doe thee and him good, prayer in this caſe for others, is a cleerer evidence of grace, then for our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Heere is comfort and encouragement, comfort for our ſelues, if members of the Church, if wee bleede with her, if we pray for her, if wee ſay, <hi>If I forget thee, O Ieruſalem, then let my right hand forget her cunning:</hi> the comfort is great, wee haue that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> thirſted for, the prayers of the Church; and this is a priviledge worth ten worlds, and a comfort beyond all apprehenſion, when a man lookes round about him and can ſay, there is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20861:9"/>a towne, I haue ſome prayers there, there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I haue ſtocke going there, nay in every ſhire, euery nation, ſome that bee enlarged when I am barren, ſome quickened when I am dull, and I am an adventurer in the Churches ſhippe, I haue a ſtocke in her treaſure, and an intereſt in her prayers; this keepes the head aboue water, and preſerues from ſinking.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For encouragement, to pray for the Church, would Gods people enter into a holy league, and tye themſelues in their ſeverall cloſets, to ſpend ſo much time weekely, or dayly in prayer, for ſome particular perſon, or place, Church, or Nation; I wonder how they ſhould miſſe; tell mee where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Churches ioynt prayers did ever miſ-carry, or proue abortiue? in what place, in what caſe, for what people? prayers haue beene made for men out of the Church, and haue ſped, witneſſe <hi>Ninivie;</hi> for men in the Church (good men, bad men) and haue ſped; prayers haue beene made by Land, and haue prevailed; on the Seas by <hi>Ianah,</hi> and haue ſped, they haue prevailed vnder the earth, in dens, and dungeons, and caues; prayers haue been made for ſicke men and haue holpe them, for dying men, for poore men, for captiues, for priſoners, and haue holpen; for men againſt perſecution, againſt temptation, againſt ſorrow, againſt beaſts, againſt men, againſt divels: prayers haue beene omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent heretofore, why not now?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Why now, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> if we were as others, Gods hand (wee knowe) is not ſhortened, his eare not heavie; but our ſinnes, our crying ripe ſinnes, hinder good things from vs?</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20861:9"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Why therefore ſet againſt thoſe ſinnes by prayer, caſt out your owne, cry downe other mens, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> out-cry them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but they cry loud. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yet prayer hath the ſtronger voyce, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> the blood of Chriſt ſpeakes better things then bloody ſins, &amp;c. Let <hi>Sodome</hi> yeeld ten holy men, <note place="margin">Gen. 18. Iames 5. Amos 7.1.2.</note> and ſhee ſhall bee ſpared, let one <hi>Elijah</hi> ſtand vp for ſtiffe-nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Iſraell, and one <hi>Amos</hi> plead for rebellious Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, and God will ſhew mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> True indeed, if we had ſuch as they, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> but our prayers are weake and faint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. They were men ſubiect to like paſſions. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 2. The prayer of the righteous is prevailing. <note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.17.</note> 3. Theſe here mentioned were new converts, yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with God for <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but here the whole Church ioyned: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> if all <hi>Iſrael</hi> might meete from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> there might be ſome hope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We may, and doe more then theſe might; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. we may meet in publique aſſemblies euery Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath: 2. theſe were but few that lived in the darke, and met in the night, and in <hi>Heſters</hi> time in their ſeverall families, and the whole State was then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, and againſt the Scriptures, and all religion was diſgraced; yet then they prevailed, much more we now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But now it is too late, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> many Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad be quite ſcattered, many men at home haue their backs and hearts quite broken, with wants, temptations, diſcouragements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Whileſt God cals in his word, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> it is not too
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20861:10"/>late, God is vſed to ſee men ſinking before he ſets in, their extremitie is his opportunitie; when <hi>Peter</hi> is within one night of the ſword, then is his time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But I haue waited, and ſee no ſucceſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> So did the Church, they pray for <hi>Peter</hi> this weeke, the next, and the next, the doores be ſtill ſhut, the chaines be ſtill on; well now they haue but one night more to waite, <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> they waite that, but ere morning all is wonne: If then we haue but one day, one night, one houre to ſpend; hope, pray, waite, that day, that night, that houre, God will be ſeene in the mount: deliverance ſhall come if prayer goe on the errand; it ever was ſo, ever ſhall be ſo, diſpute not but beleeue; there is who prayes and ſpeakes not, &amp; there is too that ſpeakes, who prayes not; if thou wilt pray, thou muſt open thy needs to God, as thy Father, through Chriſt, God-man as thy Mediatour, from God the holy Ghoſt, as the inditer of thy prayers: if thou wilt pray, thy heart muſt be 1. <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.18.</note> emptied of purpoſes of ſinne: 2. broken: 3. purged from guile by faith; which faith muſt then worke, before thou beginneſt; <note place="margin">Pſal. 86.7. And the 56.9.</note> ſay with <hi>David, I will call, and God will anſwer mee;</hi> and when thou haſt done, conclude, I haue ſpoken, and ſhall in due time and manner be anſwered; thus doe, and be ſure that thou neither begin nor end a lawfull petition (of ſuch onely we ſpeake) before thou art aware, let faith enter thy ſute, and end, and ſubſcribe it, and thou prevaileſt.</p>
            <p>Now to particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How findes the Angell Peter?</hi> Sure he cannot ſleepe this night, being vpon his life to morrow, and in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20861:10"/>all likelihood knowing of it by the Church, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, not ſure of life one day to an end, but like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be ſent for at an houres warning, as <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> head was. Notwithſtanding all this, <hi>Peter</hi> ſleeps as ſoundly as ever in his life, and wakes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out terrour; whence was this, from corruption? no; from naturall courage? no, when <hi>Peter</hi> was younger, and therefore naturally bolder, he was a diſtard: whence then? conſider the reaſons before, and it will be found, that it was from ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and confidence in God, which comfort moſt attends priſons and perſecutions: here ſee the ſtrength of ſpirituall peace and comfort.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath comforts for his children, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> that will quiet and ſupport them in any feares &amp; ſtraits, his conſolations will make a man ſleepe without a bed; liue almoſt without a ſoule: They will make one bold in danger, quiet in trouble, liue in the iawes of death: <hi>The ioy of the Lord is ſtrong,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehe. 8.</note> ſaith <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> ſtrong indeed that will carry a man over all: <hi>Peter</hi> had a ſtrong heart, that can thus ſleepe, thus wake, that can looke vpon Chaines, vpon Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, vpon Tyrants, vpon Torments, vpon Angels; (good and bad) and never breake his ſleepe for the matter. <hi>Pauls</hi> ioyes were ſtrong, <note place="margin">Act. 15</note> that made him <hi>ſing in the ſtockes: Davids</hi> ſaith ſtrong, that made him ſay, <hi>I will lye downe and ſleepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.</note> 
               <hi>I will not feare though ten thouſand riſe vp againſt me:</hi> thoſe were ſtrong and ſtrange ioyes that ſupported <hi>Dauid</hi> in all his feares, and made him ſay, <hi>In the multitude of my thoughts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94.1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>thy comforts glad my ſoule:</hi> Thoſe ſtrong that trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed over, rackings, mockings, ſcourgings, &amp;c. as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20861:11"/>in the eleventh to the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But whence comes their ſtrength? <note place="margin">1. Q Whence theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe they be Gods ioyes, the ioyes of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, derived immediately from the fountaine; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> and things be pureſt and ſtrongeſt there.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe ſpirituall, for as ſpirits are more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine and powerfull then bodies, ſo ſpirituall things then bodily and naturall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theſe ioyes are moſt certaine and durable, theſe overcome and out-liue all croſſes, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comforts.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are al-ſufficient, and borrow no helpe from creatures: Nature and Art worke with inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and by meanes, they cannot ſupport with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meate, ſtrengthen without ſleepe, giue ſleepe without warmth, nor warmth without a bed, &amp;c. But God can beyond meanes, without means, work comfort, make one ſee in the darke, liue in death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what be theſe comforts of God? <note place="margin">2. Q. What.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Precious promiſes applyed by God in due ſeaſon, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> and brought home to the heart, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viue the ſpirits more then any balme; and theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes come thicke vpon <hi>Peter</hi> now: He thinketh, hath not God ſaid; that <hi>the fighing of priſoners comes to him,</hi> that <hi>he bottles vp all our teares,</hi> that <hi>we ſhould caſt our care vpon him, and he will care for vs,</hi> that <hi>in ſix and ſeven troubles, they ſhall not come neare me,</hi> that <hi>in fire and water he will he with me,</hi> &amp; did not I heare my Saviour ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are they that are per ſecuted for righteouſneſſe ſake;</hi> reade not I how <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>I will lie downe and ſteepe,</hi> and therefore I will doe ſo too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Strengthening graces, God poures the ſpirit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20861:11"/>of faith, patience, power, courage, into his, in due time; and they raiſe the heart, as wine the fainting ſpirits; every ſaving grace is healing, is ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hourely experience of Gods care and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; dence; and a childe never ſees the loue of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo much as when he is ſicke, ſo Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now that makes them plucke vp their feete with <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſay with <hi>Paul, I know whom I haue truſted;</hi> and with the Church, <hi>Thou wilt guide vs to death;</hi> and after (as <hi>David</hi> addes) <hi>receiue to glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Speciall peace of conſcience, and ioy of the holy Ghoſt, by new expreſſions of Gods fauour, and raviſhments of heaven: then God opens heaven, and they ſee their life and crowne, and ſo are carried o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> When doth God thus comfort his? <note place="margin">3. Q. When</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> When they moſt need it, as then the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brings out her preſerues, when the childe is ſicke: firſt, when they be moſt humbled and emptie of themſelues; therefore after greateſt humiliations come greateſt conſolations, as <hi>Dauid, Abraham,</hi> and others ever found.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſpecially in the day of tryall and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, the more the Devill beſtirres him, the more God beſtirres him: thus the ſweeteſt nights that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Iacob</hi> ſpent were in the field, and ſo for <hi>Peter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 28. and 32. chap. Pſal. 219.</note> and when had <hi>David</hi> thoſe large affections to riſe at midnight, when was the Word ſo ſwcete, but when his troubles were bitter?</p>
            <p>The Vſe is double, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> 1. get theſe comforts, we get
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20861:12"/>
               <hi>aqua vitae</hi> ready againſt qualmes; Bezoar-ſtone, and cordials againſt fits: but the cordials that helpe all, is the holy Ghoſt, the Comforter; Art is blind, and often poſed; Nature weake, and often foyled; (like a bow that muſt not be drawne beyond compaſſe) onely grace and ſpirituall comfort is invincible: get this, and you may ſleepe in a dungeon, liue in the darke, want all, and yet haue all; want theſe, and a flea may breake your ſleepe; <note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> and a hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting daſh your mirth in the midſt of all friends.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let ſuch as haue ſpirituall hearts thus affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſtay themſelues here; feare not povertie, there be comforts beyond the paine of famine; feare not ſickneſſe, there be comforts beyond all fits of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: feare not death, feare not chaines, feare not any thing that you can or ſhall ſuffer: Not any thing? <note place="margin">Rev. 2.10.</note> Why, a man is ſubiect to racking, to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c. yet feare not, and why? the Lord hath comfort in all, and aboue all tribulations: when he cals a <hi>Saul</hi> to a crowne, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.</note> he makes him another man: ſo when he cals a man to a chaine, <hi>Peter</hi> is not the man in priſon he was out of priſon; at the firſt he was fearefull of a wenches word, after he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yet fleſh hung backe, <hi>Iohn</hi> the laſt Chapter, verſ. <note place="margin">Act. 5.29.4.13.</note> 18. But when put vpon it, heare his voyce, ſee his face, he can be as quiet, as comfortable, as well in priſon as ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but I finde my ſelfe afraid of words? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So was <hi>Peter</hi> at firſt. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> ſaith our Saviour, beware of men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No man ſo malicious as God is mercifull, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> ſo perilous as God is pitifull. Oh but ſay we liued
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20861:12"/>where we ſhould lie in cold irons, in the darke, bee halfe pined, ſtarved; who can beare theſe? <hi>Peter</hi> can, any can, when God cals them to it.</p>
            <p>O but ſay we were put to the fiery tryall, flames are intolerable and mercileſſe. O but flames are in Gods hands, <hi>Daniel</hi> 3. Chapter: againe, Martyrs haue had more comfort there, then in all their liues before. Oh but ſome of them haue cryed out of paines: And doe not men ſo who die in their beds too? but God hath borne them through theſe, and made them amends.</p>
            <p>O get then inward ſtrength, and that will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all feares, all torments; conclude wee with that good Martyr, if God call ever any of his to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſufferings, hee will either weaken the flame or ſtrengthen their faith; hee hath promiſed (that, which let vs liue and die in; to wit) that he will not tempt beyond ſtrength: <hi>And hee is able to doe exceeding aboundantly aboue all that wee can ſpeake or thinke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Aſſure your ſelues, the ſcare of perſecution is more then perſecution it ſelſe; therefore I ſpeake to your feares, for there is none (through Gods mercie) with vs I am ſure to bee felt (I thinke) to bee feared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame night, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> That the Lord doth often hold his people long in ſuſpence, for thoſe things which hee meanes to giue them; hee is to our ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſlow, but ſure; ſure, but ſlow; thus hee was as good as his word to <hi>Abraham,</hi> hee gaue him a ſonne, but hee held him off to the laſt houre; hee kept touch with his poſterity, brought them out of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20861:13"/>Egypt, but he deferred it till the laſt day; his bond was almoſt forfeited, yet he paid it before the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.17.41. Thus <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was long in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet at the appointed time brought forth; <note place="margin">Nal. 105.19.</note> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> long in captiuity, prayers were made, and yet <hi>Daniel</hi> could heare no anſwere till night was vpon him; <note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtles till day, &amp;c. ſo alſo the woman of Canaan, <hi>Matt.</hi> 15, and the Church heere: in all which places wee ſee, that God is mindfull of his day. 2. That hee deferres ſometime till the laſt houre be running.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of this delay is manifold. 1. God would turne our eyes backward, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> and make vs ſay; O it is iuſt God ſhould deferre me, I haue deferred him; hee called and I would not heare; prayed me againe, againe, and againe, and I would not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; therefore it is equall I ſhould call and cry, and not be heard.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God hereby would ſharpen our prayers for the preſent, therefore hee ſeemes deafe, becauſe we ſhould ſpeake out; therfore ſlow, becauſe we ſhould be earneſt; thus <hi>Daniel</hi> interprets it: God deferres him, this is (ſaith hee) but to try me, therefore he ſpits vpon his hands, and takes better hold; O Lord forgiue, ſaith hee, O Lord heare, O Lord open, and poures ſo many petitions, and arguments vpon God, that there is no reſiſtance; thus <hi>Iacob,</hi> he ſees the day comming vpon him, and he had made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it all night, and therefore now he ſets to it, <hi>Goe,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>I will not let thee goe without a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Hereby hee prepares vs for the future recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20861:13"/>of his comforts; thus he humbles vs, thus he enlargeth vs, thus fits vs for thankfulneſſe, the more bleſſings coſt vs, the better we will priſe them, and prayſe God for them: adde to this, that theſe repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes driue vs to further ſearches, <note place="margin">Ioſ. 7. Iudg. 20.</note> as the Iſraelites at <hi>Ai,</hi> and <hi>Gibeah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth the Lord thus long deferre ſometime his intended comforts and anſwers? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Let's know the courſes of his providence, and wait vpon him: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the husbandman waits; when he hath ſowne his ſeede, he doth not looke to reape and ſow all in a day, his Corne is firſt buried, yea it dies, yea it growes downeward, before it comes vpward, and when it is vp, receiues many a ſnib and checke, yet he waites? And why? becauſe he hath experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: ſo muſt wee, when we haue ſowne our ſeed; ſay we bury our prayers, ſay to our ſeeming they die, ſay they grow downeward, backward, ſay all things ſeeme to be worſe after prayer with vs then before, yet waite; why, we haue experience of our owne and other mens ſucceſſe, never did men ſow this ſeed, but they had a croppe, though a late harveſt, yet a harveſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Oh but I haue prayed exceeding long. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> How long? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Iſaack</hi> prayed twentie yeares for a childe, before he ſped, <hi>Abraham</hi> thirtie; before he ſped; <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſteritie were foure hundred yeares in captivitie, before they were delivered; the Church thirſted for Chriſt, one thouſand, two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, three thouſand yeares, before they had him: How many thouſands, hundreds, ſcores of yeares, haſt thou waited?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20861:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O but I haue tryed all my friends, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> vſed all meanes, prayed my ſelfe, and got others to ſpeake too, and yet no helpe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And might not <hi>Peter</hi> ſay as much? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> not a Chriſtian in Ieruſalem, but had ſpoken, and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken often, and yet he ſtickes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O but matters with me are worſe and worſe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> the more I pray againſt povertie, the poorer I am; the more I pray for patience, the worſe I am; the more I pray for faith, the leſſe I haue; the more I pray againſt paſſions and temptations, the more they flie in my face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is not this as we ſayd, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> that the corne muſt goe backeward, before it come forward; was it not ſo with <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> the longer they prayed the elder they waxed, and ſo vnfitter for iſſue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O but my ſinnes grow ſtronger by prayer. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not ſo, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> thou feeleſt it more then before; it is not becauſe ſinne is ſtronger, but thou ſounder; againe, theſe motions of ſinne, be not motions of life, but ſymptoms of death; as the fowle ſtruggles, and ſprunts moſt when the head is off: the panges of death be now vpon thy luſts, take comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O but now your comforts come too late, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> the date is out for me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Why? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> hath God ſayd pray no more, as to <hi>Ieremie,</hi> hath he ſtopt thy mouth? ſo long as God ſaith, pray; ſo long as the ſpirit within thee ſaith, pray; ſo long as Gods people haue hearts to pray; never ſay it is too late to pray: if <hi>Peter</hi> be out by midnight, or by day-breake, it is as well as if he had beene out a moneth before.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20861:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O but delayes breakes the heart. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But note the end of delayes, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> they are never to deny or fruſtrate, but to fit, and to quicken: make theſe vſes of delayes, and then if thy ſute be not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, never begin it; if it be, never leaue it: learne of husband men, when they pull downe a tree, or liſt at ſome blocke, if they cannot ſtirre it, they call in helpe, if it come not at the firſt pull, they pull againe, if not then, ha, againe; if not then, ha, once more; at laſt they feele it comming, and then it comes amaine: learne of <hi>Elijah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 18.43.</note> hee prayed for raine, having prayed lookes about him, nothing comes; he prayed againe, nothing comes; hee prayed againe, nothing comes; at length, O Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (ſaith his ſervant) I ſee a cloud, but it is but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; Is it a cloud? then once more to it, and by and by the heavens were masked with cloudes: learne of theſe men, <hi>Peter</hi> ſtickes in the dungeon, one lifts, he cannot ſtirre him; try you (ſaith he) to a ſecond, to a third, try a fourth, a fiſt; at length heaven ſtirres, the chaines ſtirre, and <hi>Peter</hi> comes in amongſt them: learne of Chriſt himſelfe; the widdow dealt with a Iudge, not a Father; <note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> a bad Iudge, ſhee was alone, a ſimple Orator, yet ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes: learne of beggers, they haue no command, no promiſe, no acquaintance, no Art; and yet will ſtand it out; the maſter chides, the begger ſtands it out; the dame chides, he ſtands ſtill; the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants come, and ſay they dare not ſerue him; the children ſay we muſt not, and yet he will not away. O Lord, helpe our faith, how weake be we, if ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving precept, promiſe, kindred, Gods ſervants,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20861:15"/>Gods Sonne on our ſides, we will be put off with a delay: well (as I ſaid) ſo long as a night, an houre, a minute, is left, pray; one night may compaſſe that which an hundred before could not.</p>
            <p>It followeth, <hi>An Angell, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord hath ever meanes at hand for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> comfort and deliverance, if ſet on worke; well might <hi>Peter</hi> ſay, <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord knoweth how to deliuer his, &amp;c.</hi> He is never at a ſtand, if they know how to pray, he knoweth how to comfort.</p>
            <p>In himſelfe he is al-ſufficient, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> infinite in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to invent meanes; in power, to act them; and if need be, <note place="margin">Eſa. 4.5.</note> to create more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is the Lord of Hoaſts, the Lord of every creature; if our worke lie in the Seas, he is Lord of the Seas; if on the Land, he is Lord there, if in Priſon he beareth the keyes of every Gaole; if heavens can helpe vs, he commands them; if winds, if beafts, if friends, if ſtrangers, if foes, if Angels; the Lord hath the command of all perſons, things, and places.</p>
            <p>For comfort, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> roule thy ſelfe vpon God, caſt thy care vpon him, he will bring it to paſſe; is thy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, povertie? <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> caſt it vpon him, and he will helpe it; is it ſinne, feare, ſorrow, whatſoever it be, he can beare it, and diſcharge thee?</p>
            <p>Oh but I ſee no meanes, <note place="margin">This Sermon was made in the depth of the dearth.</note> I owe ſo much; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in my familie, and no meanes.</p>
            <p>This is as if they ſhould haue ſaid, If we had a friend in the Court, to moue <hi>Herod;</hi> if a friend in the Watch, to bribe him; if in the priſon, to ſee him; then ſomething might be done, but now all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20861:15"/>meanes faile vs. No, no: God hath meanes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our ſight, if men cannot doe it, Angels can and ſhall: and if no man will pay the Widdowes debt, God will: if no body elſe will feede <hi>Eliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King 4.</note> the Ravens ſhall: what doe wee talke of meanes? all meanes are ſhut vp in God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O but my caſe is deſperate, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> it is not poſſible to helpe me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Now we ſhall haue a tale of impoſſibilities: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> And why not poſſible; ſhall any thing be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> O but there be an hundred blockes in my way. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But what is in his way, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> that makes his way through the ſeas, ſtones, wood, iron, &amp;c? <note place="margin">Eſa. 43.16.</note> goe to the priſon, there is a blocke, a guard; paſſe that guard, there is a blocke, a doore; paſſe the doore, there is another, a chaine; paſſe the chaine, there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, an iron gate. O but what of this, if they can breake through all hinderances of vnbeliefe, diſcouragements to prayer: God will breake tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row theſe and a thouſand more, to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. O but God workes no wonders now. <note place="margin">Marke our Saviours cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection from Manna to bread. Mat. 4. Deut. 8.3. Eſa. 9.6.</note> No? his Name is wonderfull ſtill; his power as great as ever, his wiſedome as deepe as ever, his promiſes as good, his loue as much to his as ever, our need as much, our intereſt as good, our Saviour as good; all things ſtand as before: if wee can vſe former meanes, we ſhall finde former ſucceſſe, and God will doe abundantly aboue all that we can ſpeake or thinke: wee haue the Lords promiſe for this, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 3.20. and <hi>Eſay</hi> 42.16. <hi>I will make darke
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20861:16"/>light, and crookedneſſe ſtraight:</hi> wee haue had our owne experience, let any man that hath had any acquaintance with God and this holy dutie, tell me when prayers were not ſucceſ-full; when didſt thou ever ſpeake to thy heavenly Father, but he did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere thee with ſome eaſe, ſome comfort? When didſt thou ever pray, but thy heart was thereby ſomewhat lightened? and if thou canſt not but ſay with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.3.</note> in the ſame day I asked, I was thus far anſwered, <hi>That my heart was ſtrengthened, Pſ.</hi> 139.3. doe not faile to conclude with <hi>David, Though I walke in the midſt of troubles, yet</hi> (vpon prayer) <hi>I ſhall be revived,</hi> 7. <hi>and God will perfect his mercies in me for ever,</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Thus wee haue diſpatcht ſome meditations: more we haue, but they muſt be onely named; as
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Herod</hi> would, but could not bring forth <hi>Peter,</hi> to tryall and execution: men be but men, and muſt doe as they may; for what they would doe againſt the Church, nor they, nor all the Divells in hell can doe.</item>
                  <item>2. The Lord can giue ſleepe and peace in any place, at any time, in any company.</item>
                  <item>3. Gods beſt ſervants and meſſengers, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times yoaked with vileſt offenders, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>4. Gods beſt creatures are the Churches ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: Angels.</item>
                  <item>5. Laſtly, the Lord can quickly ſhake his out of their chaines, rags, feares, fetters, &amp;c. But what doe I meane thus to exceede: Brethren I would faine haue you more thirſtie of your time, doe you not waſte it (as others doe) in idle impertinencies,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20861:16"/>much leſſe in ſurveying States and Kingdomes; It is not for vs to ſit vpon Crownes and thrones, and to turne Stateſmen; it is for vs to be thankefull where God bleſſes, and to be prayerfull when the Church labours; to this end I haue ſayd thus much; to perſwade you to the practice of what you know, now your turne fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, lets ſee what will be done, and how well you will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue time, in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to God; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to, or of men. (⸪)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20861:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20861:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20861:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
